Dr. Anwar Said

Office: A417 ISIS building 1025, 16th Avenue, South, Nashville, TN, 37212, USA @ anwar.said@vanderbilt.edu; Homepage Google Scholar GitHub

About

I am currently a postdoctoral research scholar at Vanderbilt University, TN. My research belongs to the area of graph representation learning (GRL), an emerging field having far-reaching applications in a diverse range of industries, from drug discovery and optimization to recommendation and forecasting. My research mainly focuses on the design of novel GRL approaches to enhance their performance and apply them to solve complex real-world problems. Working closely with a team of experts, I have developed several GRL approaches that have been applied to problems such as circuit design completion, link prediction in Ethereum data, and fraud detection in social networks. In addition to my work in GRL, I also work in data science, graph theory, and network science. Recently, I have expanded my research to include GRL applications in the field of electronic design automation as well as neuroscience. Through my research, I strive to make meaningful contributions to the field of GRL and improve our understanding of the complex systems that shape our world.

Education

Postdoctoral Research Scholar

Mar. 2021-Present

- Institute for Software Integrated Systems, Department of Computer Science, Vanderbilt University, TN, USA.
- Advisor: Prof. Xenofon Koutsoukos
- Area: Graph machine learning and its applications

Ph.D. Computer Science

Nov. 2021

- Information Technology University, Lahore, Pakistan
- Advisors: Prof. Saeed-Ul Hassan, Prof. Mudassir Shabbir
- Dissertation: Novel Graph Representations for Machine Learning Applications

M.Phil. Computer Science

Aug. 2016

- Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan
- Dissertation: Discovering Community Structure of Complex Networks
- Major Area of Study: Social Network Analysis, Graph Theory
- Minor Area of Study: Artificial Intelligence

M.Sc. Computer Science with Distinction

Dec. 2013

• University of Swat

Industry Experience

• C++ Programmer
Shaheen Foundation, Islamabad

Jul. 2014 - Sep. 2017

As a C++ programmer, my role primarily revolved around the development and implementation of advanced QT applications for a diverse range of clients. I worked

in close collaboration with a team of professionals, where my responsibilities involved not only the programming aspects but also requirement engineering, model prototyping, testing, and seamless deployment of high-quality solutions. My proficiency in C++ programming and extensive experience with QT allowed me to deliver bespoke solutions that met the unique and complex requirements of the clients.

• Graph Data Scientist

May 2021 - Mar. 2022

BUILD & CODE Germany

As a Graph Data Scientist, my responsibilities include developing advanced machine learning models for the completion of a huge knowledge graph, which contained over 10 billion data points. It was a challenging but rewarding experience to work on a project of such a massive scale, and it allowed me to gain valuable experience in handling and processing big data. I worked on a range of advanced machine learning techniques, including Graph Neural Networks (GNNs), classical ML methods, Neo4J and Cypher.

Research Experience

Vanderbilt University

Postdoctoral Research Scholar

Mar. 2022 - Present

Research Interests: Graph Machine Learning, Graph Descriptors, Circuit Design Completion, Data Science, Graph Theory

Information Technology University, Lahore

Sep. 2017 - Oct. 2022

PhD Fellow

Projects: Graph Machine Learning, Social Network Analysis, Altmetrics, Ethereum Network Analysis, Call Data Record Analysis, Federated Learning

Master Student: Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad Research areas: Community detection in social networks, Genetic Algorithms, Machine Learning Aug. 2016 - Sep. 2017

Teaching Experience

Information Technology University, Lahore

Teaching Assistant for:

Aug. 2018 - June 2020

- Advanced topics in social Network Analysis (Spring 2018)
- Information retrieval (Fall 2018)
- Database (Spring 2019)
- Data Science (Fall 2019)
- Data Structures (Spring 2020)

Instructor at Hira and Khyber Technical College, Kabal, Swat

2009 - 2011

- Physics (Undergrad/college level)
- Surveying (Undergrad/college level)
- Mathematics (Undergrad/college level)
- Chemistry (college level)

Awards and Honors

- Recipient of the Vanderbilt University, Postdoctoral Research Scholar Fellowship
- Recipient of the *travel grant* for attending the "Youth in High Dimensions: Machine Learning, High-dimensional Statistics, and Inference for the New Generation" Conference, 2020, ICTP, Trieste, Italy.
- Recipient of the Information Technology University, Ph.D. Fellowship

• Recipient of the *Gold Medal* from University of Swat for achieving highest academic ranking

Tools Developed

- Released an initial version (WiP) of our web-based application for benchmarking graph neural networks (2023). (Link to the app)
- Released a python package with reproducability check by CodeOcean for our graph augmentation framework appeared in publication entitled "On Augmenting Topological Representations for Attributed Graphs", Applied Soft Computing, 2023. (Link to the package)
- Released a python library for our graph descriptor appeared in publication entitled "DGSD: Distributed graph representation via graph statistical properties", Future Generation Computer Systems (2021). (Link to the package)
- Released Python package for CC-GA, our community detection algorithm appeared
 in publication entitled "CC-GA: A clustering coefficient based genetic algorithm for
 community detection in social networks (2018)". Every two weeks, this repository
 has an average of 100 number of clones. (Link to the package)

Publications

Under review

- 1. Said, A., Shabbir, M., Abbas, W., Derr, T., Koutsoukos, X., Empowering Graph Neural Networks using Subgraph Embeddings, PAKDD2023
- Ali, A., Said, A., Safder, I., Hassan, S., Aljohani, N.R., Shabbir, M., MSDGSD: A Scalable Graph Descriptor for Processing Large Graphs, IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems
- 3. Said, A., Ahmad, U, Abbas, W., Shabbir, M., & Koutsoukos, X. Network Controllability Perspectives on Graph Representation, IEEE Transaction on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE).
- 4. Athar, S, Abbasi, R. A., Saeed Z., Said A., ASBiNE: Dynamic Bipartite Network Embedding for Incorporating Structural and Attribute Information, WWW23.

Published

- Ahmed, A., Said, A., Shabbir, M., Koutsoukos, X., Sequential Graph Neural Networks for Source Code Vulnerability Identification, ACM Symposium on the Science of Security 2023.
- 2. Said, A., Shabbir, M., Hassan, S. U., Hassan, Z. R. & Ahmed, A. On Augmenting Topological Graph Representations for Attributed Graphs, Applied Soft Computing journal, Elsevier (2023).
- 3. Said, A., Shabbir, M., Broll, B, Volgyesi, P, Abbas, W, & Koutsoukos, X., "Circuit Design Completion Using Graph Neural Networks", journal of Neural Computing and applications (2023).
- 4. Sandborn, M., Olea, C., Said, A., Shabbir, M., Volgyesi, P., Koutsoukos, X., White, J., What a drag! Streamlining the UAV design process with design grammars and drag surrogates, the 2022 International Conference on Computational Science & Computational Intelligence (CSCI'22)

- 5. Attaullah, Abbasi, R A., Khattak, A. and Said, A. Identifying Misinformation Spreaders: A Graph-Based Semi-Supervised Learning Approach, Multimedia Evaluation Benchmark Workshop 2022
- Mian, A., Shah, S, Ullah, S., Said, A., Heimerl, K., & Crowcroft, J. A Value-Added IoT Service For Cellular Networks using Federated Learning, computer networks (2022).
- Said, A., Janjua, M. U., Hassan, S. U., Muzammal, Z., Saleem, T., Thaipisutikul, T., ... & Nawaz, R. (2021). Detailed analysis of Ethereum network on transaction behavior, community structure and link prediction. PeerJ Computer Science, 7, e815.
- 8. Said, A., Hassan, S. U., Tuarob, S., Nawaz, R., & Shabbir, M. (2021). DGSD: Distributed graph representation via graph statistical properties. Future Generation Computer Systems, 119, 166-175.
- 9. Said, A., Hassan, S. U., Abbas, W., & Shabbir, M. (2021). NetKI: A kirchhoff index based statistical graph embedding in nearly linear time. Neurocomputing, 433, 108-118.
- Hassan, S. U., Shabbir, M., Iqbal, S., Said, A., Kamiran, F., Nawaz, R., & Saif, U. (2019). Leveraging Deep Learning and SNA approaches for Smart City Policing in the Developing World. International Journal of Information Management, 102045.
- 11. Said, A., Bowman, T. D., Abbasi, R. A., Aljohani, N. R., Hassan, S. U., & Nawaz, R. (2019). Mining network-level properties of Twitter altmetrics data. Scientometrics, 120(1), 217-235.
- Said, A., Shah, S., Farooq, H., Mian, A., Imran, A., & Crowcroft, J. (2018).
 Proactive Caching at the Edge Leveraging Influential User Detection in Cellular D2D Networks. Future Internet, 10(10), 93.
- Imran, M., Akhtar, A., Said, A., Safder, I., Hassan, S. U., & Aljohani, N. R. (2018, September). Exploiting Social Networks of Twitter in Altmetrics Big Data. In 23rd STI 2018 conference, September 12-14, 2018, Leiden, The Netherlands. Centre for Science and Technology Studies (CWTS).
- 14. Said, A., Abbasi, R. A., Maqbool, O., Daud, A., & Aljohani, N. R. (2018). CC-GA: A clustering coefficient based genetic algorithm for detecting communities in social networks. Applied Soft Computing, 63, 59-70.

2020 - Present

2020-Present

2021

• International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)

• ACM Transaction on Social Computing

Referee Services Conferences

Referee Services

Journals

• Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2021 - Present
• Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (SIGKDD)	2023 - Present
\bullet International Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)	2023-Present
• Information Sciences Elsevier	2022 - Presen
Big Data Research Elsevier	2022 - Presen
Network Science	2022 - Presen
• Swarm and Evolutionary Computation (Elsevier)	2017 - Presen
• IEEE Access	2019 - Presen
IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems	2020-Present

• Journal of Ambient Intelligence and Humanized Computing (AIHC)

Mentoring (not an advisor)	Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad • Attaullah, M.Phil. Computer Science	2022
	- Co-authored "Identifying Misinformation Spreaders: A Graph-Based Semi-Supervised Learning Approach" Multimideia Eval 2022	
	• Sajjad Athar M.Phil. Computer Science	2021
	- Co-authored "ASBiNE: Dynamic Bipartite Network Embedding for Incorporating Structural and Attribute Information" ES2021	
	Information Technology University, Lahore • Muhammad Ali, Master in Computer Science	2022
	- Co-authored "MSDGSD: A Scalable Graph Descriptor for Processing Large Graphs" ITCSS 2022	
	• Ammar Ahmed, Bachelor of Computer Science	2020
	 Co-authored "Sequential Graph Neural Networks for Source Code Vulnerability Identification" HotSoS2023 	
	• Muhammad Huzaifa, Bachelor of Computer Science	2019
Invited talks/guest lectures	• Gave a guest lecture at Tennessee State University on "Machine Learning Forefront of Molecular Analysis" (march 2023)	at the
	• Graph Machine Learning in Circuit Design Completion Vanderbilt Postdoctoral Association Symposium	2022
	 Graph Neural Networks for Knowledge Graph Completion Build & Code 	2022
	• On the Analysis of Cryptocurrency Networks Blockchain Lab, ITU	2021
	• Community Detection in Social Networks Intelligent Machine Lab, ITU	2020
	• Network Analysis for Social Good STI conference 2020	2020
Certification (courses)	• Responsible Conduct of Research course (RCR) (Vanderbilt) 2022	
	• RCR training (Vanderbilt) 2022	
	• Social Network Analysis (Vanderbilt)	
	• Deep Learning (Coursera)	
	• Machine Learning (Coursera)	
	• Probability Theory (Coursera)	
	• Linear Algebra (Online MIT)	
	• Graph Machine Learning (Online Stanford)	
	• Social Network Analysis (Online Stanford)	
	• 1-year survey diploma (KPK TTB)	
	• MS Office (SDC Peshawar)	
	• AutoCAD (SDC Peshawar)	

Volunteering • Member of VPA Symposium planning committee (2023) • Volunteer at ICML 2021 $\bullet\,$ Volunteer at NeurIPS 2022 • Intro to CS @ Govt. Middle School Dhero (middle school students) 2020 • Intro to AI @ Govt. High School Kabal (high school students) 2019 • Intro to OOP @ Govt. JPG Swat (undergraduate students) 2019• Volunteer flood relief in Swat 2011 • Volunteer with "save the children" NGO, Swat 2010 • Volunteer earthquake relief in Abbottabad 2005 **Programming** • Python, Networkx, TensorFlow, Scikit-learn, PyG, PyTorch, Deep Graph Library,

Tools

Multiprocessing, SQL, Neo4J, Cypher, C++, AWS, Jira, iGraph, Message Passing Interface (MPI), Socket Programming, Tableau, Docker, MLOps, Streamlit

Research Impact Number of citations: 241

Impact factor: 69